<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Tips from Tzana</title>
    <subtitle>This is an attempt to provide relevant information during the time of crisis. This site is sponsored by Tzana Pharmaceuticals Pvt Ltd.</subtitle>
    <link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
    <link href="" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    
    <updated>2020-03-24T02:00:00+05:30</updated>
    
    <id>https://anote.in/</id>
        <entry>
            <title>What Supplements are you having?</title>
            <link href="https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-supplements/"/>
            <updated>2020-03-24T02:00:00+05:30</updated>
            <id>https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-supplements/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
                <p>When there is a pandemic, especially a viral one, there is nothing much you can do. You can stay indoors, prevent contact and boost your immunity. Your immunity is the only thing that can help at this point. So anything that boosts immunity or helps fight against viruses can be considered.</p>
<p>This by no means is an exhaustive list and I am only sharing the information we have gathered.</p>
<h2 id="do-not-consume-without-consulting-a-doctor">Do not consume without consulting a doctor <a class="anchor" href="#do-not-consume-without-consulting-a-doctor">#</a></h2>
<p>The below document only points some research and in by no means is a recommendation of drugs. You will have to speak to a doctor with your case history before having any drugs or vitamins or supplements mentioned below.</p>
<h3 id="vitamin-c">Vitamin C <a class="anchor" href="#vitamin-c">#</a></h3>
<p>Vitamin C is a no brainer. Vitamin C is a strong antioxidant and has great immunity boosting properties. A dosage of 500 mg / day for an adult should be an easy choice.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cost: Rs 15 / 15 tablets</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="vitamin-d3">Vitamin D3 <a class="anchor" href="#vitamin-d3">#</a></h3>
<p>Low Vitamin D3 levels promote viral epidemics. This is why traditionally the flu season happens in low sun seasons. Today with exposure to sun significantly low because of modern lifestyles, most people are deficient in this absolutely key vitamin .Vitamin D can reduce the risk of viral epidemics and pandemics in several ways. First, higher 25(OH)D concentrations (Vitamin D sufficiency) reduce the risk of many chronic diseases, including cancers, cardiovascular disease, chronic respiratory tract infections (RTIs), diabetes mellitus, and hypertension. Patients with chronic diseases have significantly higher risk of death from RTIs than otherwise healthy people. Second, vitamin D reduces risk of RTIs through three mechanisms: maintaining tight junctions, killing enveloped viruses through induction of cathelicidin and defensins, and reducing production of proinflammatory cytokines by the innate immune system, thereby reducing the risk of a cytokine storm leading to pneumonia. Observational and supplementation trials have reported higher 25(OH)D concentrations associated with reduced risk of dengue, hepatitis, herpesvirus, hepatitis B and C viruses, human immunodeficiency virus, influenza, respiratory syncytial virus infections, and pneumonia. [^1]</p>
<ul>
<li>Dosage recommended in studies: 1200 IU / day (Do not consume more than 4000 IU per day as it will cause Vitamin D toxicity in the long run.</li>
<li>Cost: Rs 4 / tablet of 600 IU</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="iodine">Iodine <a class="anchor" href="#iodine">#</a></h3>
<p>Iodine inactivates viruses. There are hardly any known virus in the past years which are not killed by Iodine. The salivary glands, nasal mucosa, and lungs all secrete mucus which contains iodine. But this happens only after the thyroid glad has had its fill of Iodine. Unfortunately <a href="http://iodocefol.com/brochure/iodocefol.html#sec-3-2-2">most of us are iodine difficient</a> and the thyroid gland will use up all available iodine. If the daily iodine dose is above 3 mg for over 2 weeks, the thyroid gland becomes saturated and no longer takes up much iodine. Then, dietary iodine goes to other sites named above and is excreted into the upper respiratory and gastrointestinal tract mucus. It seems logical that air borne viruses become stuck in mucus and killed by free iodine.</p>
<p>However, having 3 mg of Iodine will not be advised by doctors as our current RDA guidelines are at 150 micrograms of Iodine per day.</p>
<h3 id="ayurveda">Ayurveda <a class="anchor" href="#ayurveda">#</a></h3>
<p>If you have access to professional Ayurveda doctors, you could inquire on immunity boosting medicines in Ayurveda. There are quite a few of them. I recently learned that the Dasamoola Jeerakaarishtam is one of them. But please get your suggestions from doctors.</p>
<p>[^1] <a href="https://www.preprints.org/manuscript/202003.0235/v1">https://www.preprints.org/manuscript/202003.0235/v1</a></p>

            ]]></content>
        </entry>
        <entry>
            <title>A note on Iodine</title>
            <link href="https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-a-note-on-iodine/"/>
            <updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
            <id>https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-a-note-on-iodine/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
                <h1 id="povidone-iodine">Povidone Iodine <a class="anchor" href="#povidone-iodine">#</a></h1>
<p>Povidone-iodine (PVP-I), also known as iodopovidone, is an antiseptic used for skin disinfection. In a study conducted in Japan [^1] PVP-I was fouond to be effective in inactivating a range of viruses including adeno-, mumps, rota-, polio- (types 1 and 3), coxsackie-, rhino-, herpes simplex, rubella, measles, influenza and human immunodeficiency viruses. PVP-I is found to be very effective and viruses doesnt seem to have developed any form of resistence to this antiseptic.</p>
<h2 id="what-can-we-do-with-iodine">What can we do with Iodine <a class="anchor" href="#what-can-we-do-with-iodine">#</a></h2>
<p>Aerosol iodine was found to kill viruses in sprayed mists, and solutions ofiodine were equally effective. In 1945, Burnet and Stone found that putting iodine on mice snouts pre-vented the mice from being infected with live influenza virus in mists. They suggested that impregnatingmasks  with  iodine  would  help  stop  viral  spread. They  also  recommended  that  medical  personnel  haveiodine-aerosol-treated rooms for examination and treatment of highly infected patients. Current methodsof dealing with influenza infection are isolation, hand washing, antiviral drugs, and vaccinations. All ofthese methods can be improved by incorporating iodine into them. When impregnated with iodine, masksbecome much more effective, and hand washing is more effect when done with mild iodine solutions.Isolation techniques coupled with aerosol iodine would make them safer for patients, medical personnel,and all persons working with the public. Public health authorities could organize the distribution of iodineand at the same time educate the public in the effective use of iodine. Oral iodine might also boost bodydefense mechanisms in the upper oral and respiratory mucus. [^2]</p>
<h2 id="how-can-we-use-pvp-i">How can we use PVP-I <a class="anchor" href="#how-can-we-use-pvp-i">#</a></h2>
<p>Go to your pharmacy and purchase Betadine solutions or Povidone Iodine Solution. Depending on the brand you get the price will vary hugely. For e.g Betadine is 10% solution with 1% free Iodine and costs Rs 102. If you go to Jan Oushadhi you get a 5% solution with 0.5% Free Iodine for Rs 19! Get any.</p>
<p>You can use the solution the following ways:</p>
<ol>
<li>Aerosol - Dilute the Iodine solution from 10% to 0.5% by adding 20 times water (or 5% to 0.5% by adding 10 times water) to the solution and put it in a glass cleaner solution bottle or a regular spray bottle. Turn on the fan and spray into it, keeping your eyes closed, the liquid will disperse nicely into the air and will inactivate any virus in the air.</li>
<li>Disinfectant - Use the same dilution as above and wipe floors and surfaces using this liquid.</li>
<li>Masks - Take three pieces of cloth 10cm by 15cm. Dip one piece of cloth in the liquid of (2) above and dry it. Use this piece as a middle layer, stick the the three together and attach elastic to go around your ear. You have your own anticeptic mask.</li>
<li>Gargle - Dilute to the same 20 times level as above and gargle without swallowing. To be fair research has actually shown that just gargling with water has better effect than even PVP. So I’d recommend gargling on a regular basis. This is shown to prevent getting upper respiratory diseases. COVID19 is one of them.</li>
</ol>
<p>[^1] <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9403252">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9403252</a><br>
[^2] <a href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/bc37/c48fb2babb83d333d9e4193bf7960040222d.pdf?_ga=2.71665627.938116286.1584968335-388329458.1584968335">https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/bc37/c48fb2babb83d333d9e4193bf7960040222d.pdf?_ga=2.71665627.938116286.1584968335-388329458.1584968335</a></p>

            ]]></content>
        </entry>
        <entry>
            <title>How to make your own Hand Sanitizers</title>
            <link href="https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-how-to-make-hand-sanitizer/"/>
            <updated>2020-03-23T19:30:00+05:30</updated>
            <id>https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-how-to-make-hand-sanitizer/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
                <p>Hand sanitizers have been recommended by the WHO to sanitize your hands in case you do not wash you hands with soap. Washing with soap (any soap) is still considered the best way to disinfect your hands. While you are at it, wash your face and arm with soap as well if you can. In case you cant wash, use a hand sanitizer.</p>
<p>There are two hand sanitizers that the WHO recommends you can use.</p>
<ol>
<li>Ethyl alcohol based hand sanitizer and</li>
<li>Isopropyl alcohol based hand sanitizer.</li>
</ol>
<p>Ethy alcohol (or Ethanol) based hand sanitizers are the cheapest to make, but ethanol is a restricted substance in most countries and it might not be easy to obtain it. Because of that I will be focussing on isopropyl alcohol (or propanol) based sanitizer. I will leave a link at the bottom to the WHO article which has both recipes.</p>
<h2 id="propanol-based-hand-sanitizer">Propanol based Hand sanitizer <a class="anchor" href="#propanol-based-hand-sanitizer">#</a></h2>
<p>All ingredients for this can be obtained from a pharmacy or an online chemist.</p>
<h4 id="recipe">Recipe <a class="anchor" href="#recipe">#</a></h4>
<ol>
<li>Rubbing Alcohol (Iso-propyl alcohol) - 760 ml</li>
<li>Glycerine - 15 ml ( a 100 ml bottle costs Rs 32)</li>
<li>3% Hydrogen Peroxide - 40 ml ( a 100ml bottle costs Rs 14 for 6% solution.) (Optional)</li>
<li>Water - 185 ml</li>
<li>Few drops of perfume (Optional)</li>
</ol>
<p>A note on hydrogen peroxide: Hydrogen peroxide in the recipe is a 3% solution. If what you get from the pharmacy is a 6% solution, just use half of the quantity above. For the purpose of Covid-19, if you cant find Hydrogen peroxide, its fine as the purpose of hydrogen peroxide is to kill bacteria and fungal spores.</p>
<h4 id="method">Method <a class="anchor" href="#method">#</a></h4>
<p>Mix all of the above in a closed bottle. Shake it a little and you are done.</p>
<p>If you want to make this liquid a little nourishing, I would recommend adding 50ml of Aloe vera gel to it and it will do good to your skin.</p>
<p>It is as simple as that.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.who.int/gpsc/5may/Guide_to_Local_Production.pdf">The WHO Link to the article is here</a>.</p>

            ]]></content>
        </entry></feed>