<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Tips from Tzana</title>
    <subtitle>This is an attempt to provide relevant information during the time of crisis. This site is sponsored by Tzana Pharmaceuticals Pvt Ltd.</subtitle>
    <link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
    <link href="" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    
    <updated>2020-03-20T19:30:00+05:30</updated>
    
    <id>https://anote.in/</id>
        <entry>
            <title>How to make your own Hand Sanitizers</title>
            <link href="https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-how-to-make-hand-sanitizer/"/>
            <updated>2020-03-20T19:30:00+05:30</updated>
            <id>https://anote.in/posts/2020-03-23-how-to-make-hand-sanitizer/</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
                <p>Hand sanitizers have been recommended by the WHO to sanitize your hands in case you do not wash you hands with soap. Washing with soap (any soap) is still considered the best way to disinfect your hands. While you are at it, wash your face and arm with soap as well if you can. In case you cant wash, use a hand sanitizer.</p>
<p>There are two hand sanitizers that the WHO recommends you can use.</p>
<ol>
<li>Ethyl alcohol based hand sanitizer and</li>
<li>Isopropyl alcohol based hand sanitizer.</li>
</ol>
<p>Ethy alcohol (or Ethanol) based hand sanitizers are the cheapest to make, but ethanol is a restricted substance in most countries and it might not be easy to obtain it. Because of that I will be focussing on isopropyl alcohol (or propanol) based sanitizer. I will leave a link at the bottom to the WHO article which has both recipes.</p>
<h2 id="propanol-based-hand-sanitizer">Propanol based Hand sanitizer <a class="anchor" href="#propanol-based-hand-sanitizer">#</a></h2>
<p>All ingredients for this can be obtained from a pharmacy or an online chemist.</p>
<h4 id="recipe">Recipe <a class="anchor" href="#recipe">#</a></h4>
<ol>
<li>Rubbing Alcohol (Iso-propyl alcohol) - 760 ml</li>
<li>Glycerine - 15 ml ( a 100 ml bottle costs Rs 32)</li>
<li>3% Hydrogen Peroxide - 40 ml ( a 100ml bottle costs Rs 14 for 6% solution.) (Optional)</li>
<li>Water - 185 ml</li>
<li>Few drops of perfume (Optional)</li>
</ol>
<p>A note on hydrogen peroxide: Hydrogen peroxide in the recipe is a 3% solution. If what you get from the pharmacy is a 6% solution, just use half of the quantity above. For the purpose of Covid-19, if you cant find Hydrogen peroxide, its fine as the purpose of hydrogen peroxide is to kill bacteria and fungal spores.</p>
<h4 id="method">Method <a class="anchor" href="#method">#</a></h4>
<p>Mix all of the above in a closed bottle. Shake it a little and you are done.</p>
<p>If you want to make this liquid a little nourishing, I would recommend adding 50ml of Aloe vera gel to it and it will do good to your skin.</p>
<p>It is as simple as that.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.who.int/gpsc/5may/Guide_to_Local_Production.pdf">The WHO Link to the article is here</a>.</p>

            ]]></content>
        </entry></feed>